<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ayazhafiz.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://ayazhafiz.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-19T23:38:04-06:00</updated><id>https://ayazhafiz.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ayaz Hafiz</title><subtitle>Hafiz's public website.</subtitle><author><name>hafiz</name><email>ayaz.hafiz.1@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">on understanding</title><link href="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/on-understanding" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="on understanding" /><published>2020-05-16T03:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-16T03:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/on-understanding</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/on-understanding">&lt;p&gt;A juice diet is a fad. If it is to be ubiquitous, equity is not. Neither is the elimination of
racism, or the distribution of healthcare, or the raising of millions out of poverty, or the safety
or artificial intelligence, or the protection of endangered species, or any number of other things
you or I may wish to see succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s call these &lt;strong&gt;hard problems&lt;/strong&gt;. These are problems large communities are passionate about, and
cannot be solved in five, twenty, or even fifty years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases, the general population’s commitment to these problems seems to follow that of a
fad&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;feels-fad&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;feels-fad&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;I am not saying this distribution is anywhere near representative; it is simply how it feels to me.&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/exp_of_exp.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;time vs perceived number of people committed to an issue&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the tail end, the number of people involved in resolving an issue converges to a value determined
by a function of how many communities want resolution of the issue, how many don’t, and how many are
indifferent. Note that only the first factor necessarily increases the convergent value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This convergence is expected – the world can’t dedicate all of its resources to one thing, and it’s
the whole reason for specialization. But if you are invested in an issue, and you want to see it
succeed, be committed to it. Not doing so is &lt;a href=&quot;#on-nomenclature&quot;&gt;dangerous&lt;/a&gt;; because these kinds of
issues take a very long time to solve, an initial high investment in a topic may cause workstreams
in that domain to continue expecting a similar investment. If the investment suddenly declines,
projects quickly fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#prelude&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hope is this cc will encourage you to consider your world in a larger scope, ask more questions
about it, and recalculate your reality. It’s nice to sit around, sharing fundraisers and correcting
misinformation, believing there are a well-defined set of steps we all can take to solve a common
problem. But this is naive and unrealistic; if it were so easy, no problem would be hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ideas apply to many things, but the context of this cc is social problems. To that end, it
doesn’t matter how many anti-racism protests you attend or how much money you donate towards
eliminating homelessness if you can’t empathize with affected communities. Without empathy, you will
quickly reach a barrier in your understanding another’s needs&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;russia&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;russia&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;This comes from my experience in
Russia – a white person who has only ever known other whites may not be a racist, but there is also
no way for them to stand up for a black person (or any minority) in an effective manner.&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope the perspectives in this cc are of some use to you. At the same time, they are the thoughts
of a single individual and should be scrutinized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-perspective&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#on-perspective&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;On perspective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important for you and I to understand the roles we play in the problems we are invested in.
Failing to understand this unsyncs our expectations with others’, which derailing priorities and
causing internal conflicts. Understanding this is one part of &lt;a href=&quot;#on-the-big-picture&quot;&gt;the big picture&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experiences of one individual will never be exactly like that of another.
Commonalities can be found, but claiming lived experience of another’s life is absurd. This is why
empathy and &lt;a href=&quot;#on-research&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; become pivotal skills to master; you will never live
another’s experience, but you can learn to empathize and try to understand another’s perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must learn others’ perspectives if we are committed to solving problems together. There is a
common mantra here that goes something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Give people the help that they need, not the help you think they need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;because if we only give the help we think others need, at best we’ve fallen out of sync, and at
worst we’ve derailed the mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There as a second, more subtle point to the above statement – hard problems are not about any one
individual, and there are very rarely single heroes in their solutions. A good solution requires
understanding the needs of hundreds of millions of people, which one individual can rarely do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, though every individual has a contribution to make, the solutions to such problems are
moonshots. And because nothing is perfect, an actions of an individual to help one group may be
regressive to another group (see &lt;a href=&quot;#on-intersectionality&quot;&gt;intersectionality&lt;/a&gt; below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;go&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#go&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;go!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe this seems romantic. If that’s case, do &lt;a href=&quot;#on-research&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; and speak to people involved
in the things you care about. Keep sharing instagram stories and correcting ignorant statements, but
recognize that without deeply understanding an issue, one’s actions are limited and often naive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-intersectionality&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#on-intersectionality&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;On intersectionality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because no two individuals have the same lived experiences or perspectives, it’s impossible to
design an exhaustive solution to an issue&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;full-employment&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;full-employment&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;In mathematics, this is the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Full_employment_theorem&quot;&gt;full employment theorem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;. I’m not
saying we shouldn’t shoot for solutions that solve problems for everyone, but what I am saying is
that we can’t spend all our time just looking for the “perfect” one because then nothing ever gets
done, and no one is better off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is much more important is to shoot for milestones - maybe solutions that cover 90% of the
problem, then 95%, then 99%, then 99.9%, and so on. Milestones prove that things are getting done,
which is useful for morale and future investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also shouldn’t pretend that a 100% solution is ever readily available. It’s difficult to know the
needs of everyone because the most relevant solutions will always focus on the needs of the majority
of affected populations. No one can ever come out and say, “okay, I’ve solved X hard problem,” because
they’ve certainly failed to consider an intersectionality&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;intersectionality&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;intersectionality&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intersectionality&quot;&gt;Intersectionality&lt;/a&gt; is the
idea that some issues faced by an individual are formed by a combination of identities rather than
a single one. For example, some issues faced a black woman are because they are black &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; a woman,
rather than because they or black or a woman.&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of intersectionalities, the 90% solution may be orthogonal to solutions for the other 10%.
As an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Consider ten people sleeping in a room. The room gets very hot, so one person turns on the cooler.
But one person in the room is sleeping below the AC vent, and wakes up sick the next day. Despite
the person being hot, simply turning on the AC did not fix all of their problems; the best solution
for them is to move away from the vent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s pivotal that milestones don’t regress on the status quo. Of course, this itself is a hard problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-the-big-picture&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#on-the-big-picture&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;On the big picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s always important to step back and look at the big picture&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;big-picture&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;big-picture&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;This is a vague term; for me the big picture is
every level above the one currently being looked from.&lt;/span&gt;. There are at least two reasons for this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It forces one to consider the goal in the context of an environment with more stakeholders. As an
example related to the previous section, maybe the problem can’t be wholly solved right now, but
getting a smaller win proves progress is being made, raising interest and laying the foundation
for future work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not everyone in the picture is aligned with your goals; maybe not even those you collaborate with.
Failing to recognize the motivations of others is dangerous because it pushes you further out of
understanding the context you are working in, and makes it more difficult to react to unexpected
events. Taking help and trusting others is pivotal to achieving your goals, but such trust can’t
be ignorant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-research&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#on-research&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;On research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, most answers to questions are designed to get the reader to take a specific perspective (this
post is no different). So how do you find a definitive answer to something? In some sense, you
can’t – at most, you can take samples of a number of different answers and aggregate them into
your own understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trust is difficult. Bill Gates found it difficult, so he started his own foundation instead of
donating all his money to existing funds. So before you convince yourself you understand something,
make sure you do research and are confident in your interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-nomenclature&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#on-nomenclature&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;On nomenclature&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The canonical usage of “problematic” is dangerous. Without a description of why something is
“problematic”, saying something is “problematic” is equivalent to saying, “this statement says
something bad, but I’m not going to tell you what it is or why it’s bad”. In that context,
everything can be described as “problematic”, which is useless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, it is much more useful to describe an idea as dangerous, and explain why it is so.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>hafiz</name><email>ayaz.hafiz.1@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">A juice diet is a fad. If it is to be ubiquitous, equity is not. Neither is the elimination of racism, or the distribution of healthcare, or the raising of millions out of poverty, or the safety or artificial intelligence, or the protection of endangered species, or any number of other things you or I may wish to see succeed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">heterogeneity in volunteering</title><link href="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/heterogeneity-in-volunteering" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="heterogeneity in volunteering" /><published>2020-05-16T03:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-16T03:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/heterogeneity-in-volunteering</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/heterogeneity-in-volunteering">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note: This article is written with regard to ad-hoc volunteer programs, and
less so with regard to long-standing, consistent volunteering commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went volunteering this past weekend for the first time since late March 2020
(around when the covid-19 pandemic began taking large swing in the U.S.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are the characteristics of an individual who, during a pandemic, goes to
volunteer at a home for those experiencing homelessness? In my opinion, such an
individual is fairly invested in volunteering in this space. But what
surprised me about this session was the vast diversity of my fellow volunteers’
motivations for volunteering at the home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A senior couple told me they were excited to give someone a meal and help
contribute to the home’s rehabilitation program.
They wanted to see men experiencing homelessness get an education, find a job, and obtain
stable housing. The two, working with their local church, produce personal care
bags handed out to those they see living on the streets. Only once has a
recipient of a bag asked them for money instead&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;bag&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;bag&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;This surprised me a lot. My
first impression was this would an example of giving presumed help, not the help
someone actually needs.&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lawyer 25 years my senior said she was there to say hi to the men, many of
whom were now her close friends. As a side effect of her contribution for the
day, she would take home the egg shells and cardboard cartons for thirty dozen
eggs, which she gave to her composting and flower-growing neighbors
respectively. Why was she volunteering at this home? Well, it is quite
enjoyable and meaningful as a sense of community for her. In
fact, aside her apartment, this is the only indoor location she has been in since
the pandemic has taken large swing; she has not even ordered food in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for me, I came because I wanted to speak to men experiencing homelessness
and learn how the pandemic has affected their livelihoods. It was my first time at
this home, and I wanted to learn about the experiences of the administrators of
the home, how the home operates, what the men in the home find challenging about
the home’s operations, and what unique initiatives the home drives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I list these motivations because they are very different, well-formed
perspectives.
Perhaps I had not noticed such diversities in reasoning in
previous volunteerings, perhaps I needed a several-month break, perhaps
this diversity is just characteristic to a group of individuals that would
volunteer in such a time, or perhaps something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In previous volunteerings, I found that the motivations of my fellow volunteers were
often “non-interesting” – they were there to complete a requirement, try something new,
or just learn about a cause. For me, new insights and perspectives would come
from those impacted by the volunteering, and rarely from my peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I learned the most from my peers. This was such a great thing! I
felt surrounded by passionate, genuinely dedicated individuals in a way that I
had not before. It felt like a team in a way that I had not seen from ad-hoc
volunteer programs before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am hungry to find more such programs. I write this as a retrospective,
inviting you to find such environments as well. And if you’re already a
part of one, I’d love to hear about your experience.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>hafiz</name><email>ayaz.hafiz.1@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Note: This article is written with regard to ad-hoc volunteer programs, and less so with regard to long-standing, consistent volunteering commitments.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">beauty</title><link href="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/beauty" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="beauty" /><published>2020-04-16T03:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-04-16T03:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/beauty</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/beauty">&lt;p&gt;There’s this great quote from one of Zhu’s songs&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;cocaine-model&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;cocaine-model&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/Skt_NKI4d6U?t=20&quot;&gt;Cocaine Model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; that has long influenced me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When I was seven, my father said, “Fashion fades, but beauty is eternal. Elegance is illumination.
Blue is a language. Love and obsession is separated by a thin line, and that line is infatuation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s broadly characterize human beauty as either normative or personal. Normative beauty attempts
to please the norm (of which there may be several), while personal beauty attempts to please the
self (of which there may be a few, but certainly not many). Normative beauty and personal beauty
don’t have to be disjoint, and both can be influenced environmentally. But personal beauty, when
realized, is always elegant to the self; unfortunately, the same cannot be said for normative
beauty&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;touch-beauty&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;touch-beauty&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;For example, consider the disparity between what is beautiful to
the eye and what is beautiful to the touch.&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding how an individual differentiates things like this has a tremendous influence on their
relationships. Whereas obsession decays into a desire to appease an individual’s perceived needs,
love is characterized by an understanding of their needs. These states are distinct, but may be
subtle; perhaps that subtly is infatuation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>hafiz</name><email>ayaz.hafiz.1@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">There’s this great quote from one of Zhu’s songsCocaine Model that has long influenced me:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">scaling up</title><link href="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/scaling-up" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="scaling up" /><published>2020-03-29T03:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-03-29T03:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/scaling-up</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/scaling-up">&lt;p&gt;There’s this not-so-novel idea that a businesses will often find success by focusing on inputs
rather than outputs. The reasoning is that outputs are affected by many more externalities
that inputs, and that a strong application of a business’s inputs will naturally lead to
desired outputs. For example, a salesperson may wish to focus more on the number of meetings they
set up rather than their conversion rate&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;number-meetings&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;number-meetings&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;The latter is less
deterministic than the former, and finding success in the former will lead to a larger number of
conversions anyway.&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But business must consider a number of other strategies, including how to scale up.
Observing the current&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;current&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;current&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;At the time of this writing&lt;/span&gt; COVID-19 pandemic, I
have become convinced that effective scaling is a pivotal consideration for all organizations, not
just businesses, and will play a tremendous role in the pandemic’s impact on human livelihoods. I’ll
give just three examples (you could find many more!):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Insurance premiums will soar after (and possibly during) this pandemic. Part of this will be
because a lot of people will get sick and insurance companies need to maintain short-term
profitability. Part of this is that insurance companies, like many nations’ healthcare systems,
are unprepared to scale for catastrophe.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the pandemic begins to stabilize, many individuals will need convenient, flexible
sources of income. Businesses in the gig economy, like rideshare and delivery apps, will be
stressed to intake a tremendous userbase without meticulous foresight.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I planned to immigrate to Switzerland in May, prior to the nation’s suspension of work visas.
Due to an increased backlog and higher workload, Swiss consulates estimate the processing time of
a visa to increase to over a month&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;month&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;month&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;​&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sim4\text{x}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/span&gt; the regular
processing time&lt;/span&gt; after the suspension is lifted. Could this timeline
be improved with a buffer, like delaying the start date of an issued visa?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I anticipate that we will think about scale much more as COVID rages on, and that scaling solutions
will resurge as a &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/20/satellites#4--fact&quot;&gt;fact&lt;/a&gt; in a post-COVID world. Part of the
difficulty with scaling is that it is not cheap, and without an expectation for long-term need,
arguments for scalability are dulled. It will be interesting to see how these challenges are solved.
My bet is on an economy of platforms and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bring-it-back&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#bring-it-back&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;bring it back&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generalizing&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;generalization&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;generalization&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Pun intended :slightly_smiling_face:&lt;/span&gt; the idea of
“scaling up”, one can thinking about going from a specialization to a generalization. Scale in this
sense can be very individual – it’s one thing to understand how much salt a scrambled egg requires,
it’s another to understand the same for an arbitrary dish.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>hafiz</name><email>ayaz.hafiz.1@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">There’s this not-so-novel idea that a businesses will often find success by focusing on inputs rather than outputs. The reasoning is that outputs are affected by many more externalities that inputs, and that a strong application of a business’s inputs will naturally lead to desired outputs. For example, a salesperson may wish to focus more on the number of meetings they set up rather than their conversion rateThe latter is less deterministic than the former, and finding success in the former will lead to a larger number of conversions anyway..</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">satellites</title><link href="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/satellites" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="satellites" /><published>2020-02-29T02:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-02-29T02:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/satellites</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/satellites">&lt;p&gt;At some point, all fads were satellite ideas pursued by one more independent groups. As a fad grows,
so does the size and number of groups associated with it. Eventually a fad achieves a non-trivial
adoption rate (becomes a fact) or fades away (becomes an artifact).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationships of groups pursuing an idea at all of these stages is well studied, especially
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2212827114003709&quot;&gt;with&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0956522104000272&quot;&gt;respect&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/isr/article-abstract/11/3/523/1796789?redirectedFrom=fulltext&quot;&gt;to&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Complexity_of_Cooperation&quot;&gt;collaboration and competition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;four-links&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;four-links&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;These are four separate links :slightly_smiling_face:&lt;/span&gt;.
In this cc, I wish to briefly discuss the consequences of each of these stages on individual
productivity and efficiency. Let’s start from the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4--fact&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#4--fact&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;el&quot;&gt;4:&lt;/span&gt;  Fact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intuition might suggest that productivity is lowered significant after a fad becomes a fact. But
while there may not be a lot of effort required in growing the fact to a greater level of adoption,
maintenance is non-trivial. For example, the upfront cost of building a new house is high, but this
cost is marginal relative to the maintenance costs required over the better part of the next
century&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;maintenance&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;maintenance&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Maintenance requires both individual contribution (time) and
transient contributions (e.g. via money paid for services) of productivity.&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An individual may expect a consistent maintenance cost associated with a fact. This cost is likely
to be small compared to an individual’s other responsibilities, and an increase in maintenance costs
incites an individual to develop optimizations&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;maintenance-cost&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;maintenance-cost&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;E.g. a system
that requires a lot of manual tuning is likely to be superseded.&lt;/span&gt; (read: new satellite ideas).
This can lead to a cycle of individual effort invested in an idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3--artifact&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#3--artifact&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;el&quot;&gt;3:&lt;/span&gt;  Artifact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a fad becomes an artifact, an individual has two choices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Invest more time in the artifact. This boosts individual productivity, but is
inefficient when the fad has been shown to be flawed. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://nlp.seas.harvard.edu/NamedTensor.html&quot;&gt;untyped tensors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pivot to another idea. This may lead to a loss of productivity in the short term due to ramp-up
investment, but increases efficiency in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside these considerations, the productivity invested in an artifact is very similar to that of a
fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2--fad&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#2--fad&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;el&quot;&gt;2:&lt;/span&gt;  Fad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so here’s where it gets interesting. I’m not convinced that being involved with a fad is
productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s the hot thing right now? Whatever it is, I’m sure there are a lot of people working on it.
Realistically, if any one individual working on that fad ceased their contribution immediately,
whatever they could have discovered would be independently discovered in the next &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/15_minutes_of_fame&quot;&gt;15 minutes of
fame&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong – 10% contributions add up. But for the individual, 10% isn’t always enough.
This seems like a degradation in individual efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1--satellite&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#1--satellite&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;el&quot;&gt;1:&lt;/span&gt;  Satellite&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, satellite ideas require a large efficiency investment. Whether this translates to
heightened productivity is largely dependent on personal motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satellites are lonely. Work on divergent ideas must be self-motivated, as invested dependents
are often lacking. When a road map is unclear (as is often the case for satellite ideas), it can be
difficult to convince oneself to be going. So a satellite must be really into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that this facet is often overlooked. Revolutionary ideas are good ideas, and they are also
incredibly unique and obsessively pursued. In fact, uniqueness and investment are the primary
factors that can promote a satellite into a fad. The soundness of an idea becomes more important
only later on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>hafiz</name><email>ayaz.hafiz.1@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">At some point, all fads were satellite ideas pursued by one more independent groups. As a fad grows, so does the size and number of groups associated with it. Eventually a fad achieves a non-trivial adoption rate (becomes a fact) or fades away (becomes an artifact).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">apathy</title><link href="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/apathy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="apathy" /><published>2020-02-03T02:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-02-03T02:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/apathy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/20/apathy">&lt;p&gt;Discussions of apathy generally refer to the normative kind. This kind of apathy is characterized by
an indifference to a context that one has the privilege to interface with. There are many
reasons one may be apathetic – common arguments propose convenience or
indifference&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;indifference&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;indifference&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Of course, indifference and apathy are synonymous.&lt;/span&gt;.
More difficult explanations extend medical conditions and social influences; apathy is a consequence
of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://neuro.psychiatryonline.org/doi/full/10.1176/jnp.17.1.7&quot;&gt;number of neurological diseases&lt;/a&gt;
and is propagated by communities that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/dave_meslin_the_antidote_to_apathy&quot;&gt;romanticize born heroes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;bornhhero&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;bornhhero&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;I find it hard to believe that apathetic populations are inherently impartial. I argue that societies with strict representations of success model a majority of individuals to be inconsequential. By design, this pressures a feeling of unimportance even for the self-motivated.&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a kind of apathy often overlooked. Let’s call it budgeted apathy. This kind of
apathy is characterized by an indifference to a context that is orthogonal or abstracted by
one’s priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s one example – a low-income family living in an expensive city may not have the time to think
about the long-term health effects of the fast food they consume&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;example&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;example&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This is not meant to be an anecdotal or accurate example. It’s just an example.&lt;/span&gt;.
There are at least two reasons why this might be the case: the family values fast food’s
accessibility more than it discounts adverse effects, or the family is ignorant of fast food’s
adverse health effects. I argue that there is a possible third reason: the family is indifferent to
the health effects of fast food. Note that this third reason is characterized neither by an
evaluation of priorities nor by ignorance, but by an orthogonality of primary and secondary needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Budgeted apathy is subtle; by design, it is equivalent to an orchestration of an individual’s
demands. On the other hand, it’s really just a convolution of the idea that an individual
focuses on what immediately affects them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;go&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#go&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;go!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe this is a nice idea, but it’s missing some action. One we all can take is advocacy for and
appreciation of others’ contexts. This is a little more abstract than walking in another’s shoes; it
requires a trust in individuals’ motivation, no matter how disparate they are from our own. Albeit
romantic, this is a simple, extraordinarily compassionate perspective.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>hafiz</name><email>ayaz.hafiz.1@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Discussions of apathy generally refer to the normative kind. This kind of apathy is characterized by an indifference to a context that one has the privilege to interface with. There are many reasons one may be apathetic – common arguments propose convenience or indifferenceOf course, indifference and apathy are synonymous.. More difficult explanations extend medical conditions and social influences; apathy is a consequence of a number of neurological diseases and is propagated by communities that romanticize born heroes⊕I find it hard to believe that apathetic populations are inherently impartial. I argue that societies with strict representations of success model a majority of individuals to be inconsequential. By design, this pressures a feeling of unimportance even for the self-motivated..</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">analog algorithms</title><link href="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/19/analog-algorithms" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="analog algorithms" /><published>2019-12-30T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-12-30T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/19/analog-algorithms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/19/analog-algorithms">&lt;p&gt;Most algorithms are designed for computation in a Turing machine. But Turing
machines don’t encompass the physics of the universe, and of course there are
algorithms designed to operate with other mechanics. Let’s call these other
algorithms Analog Algorithms. Here’s one that claims to sort a set of numbers in
linear time&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;Turing-linear&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;Turing-linear&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;If executed on a simulating Turing machine.&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h4 id=&quot;algorithm-spaghetti-sort&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#algorithm-spaghetti-sort&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;Algorithm &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spaghetti_sort&quot;&gt;Spaghetti Sort&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Given an unsorted set of $n$ rational numbers
$S = \{s_1, \ldots, s_n\}\quad s_i \in \mathbb{Q}$:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Obtain a set of spaghetti rods
$R = \{r_1, \ldots, r_n\}\quad len(r_i) = s_i$. Form a fist around the
rods.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Repeat until there are no more rods in the fist:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Hit one end of the spaghetti rods perpendicularly against a table, such
that the rods are aligned on that end.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Lower a hand on the other side of the rods until it touches a spaghetti
rod $r_i$.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Remove the rod $r_i$ from the fist and place it at the end of the sorted
output set.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parts of this sort may seem decidedly non-linear&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;not-Turing&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;not-Turing&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Or at least very expensive, since we’re not necessarily dealing with Turing machines.&lt;/span&gt;.
What is the time bound for lowering a hand? How do we decide where to lower the hand
from? If the hand placement is decided visually, what is the cost of synaptic transmission?
And what is the cost of sensory response from the other hand touching the longest
rod? How do we account for the size of a hand needed to hold a very large number
of rods?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, the spaghetti sort seems reasonable, in at least the sense that this is
how I would sort a set of spaghetti rods. And in celebration of the New Year, I
propose another analog algorithm, this one solving the
NP-complete&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;def-NP-complete&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;def-NP-complete&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Problems in the class NP are those whose solutions can be verified in polynomial time by a non-deterministic Turing machine. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NP-completeness&quot;&gt;NP-completeness&lt;/a&gt; refers to the class of problems hardest in NP. Every problem in NP can be transformed to an equivalent NP-complete problem.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clique_problem&quot;&gt;clique problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h4 id=&quot;algorithm-new-years-cliquer&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#algorithm-new-years-cliquer&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;Algorithm New Year’s Cliquer&lt;/h4&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Given an undirected graph $G$ with vertices $V = \{v_1, \ldots, v_n\}$ and
edges $E = \{v_i \leftrightarrow v_j, \ldots\}$:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Gather a group of people $P = \{p_1, \ldots, p_n\}$ and for each edge
$v_i \leftrightarrow v_j = e \in E$, introduce $p_i$ and $p_j$. Ensure that
each introduction results in an equivalent-strength friendship.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Institute a universal aid policy that provides each person the opportunity
to visit their new friends for the New Year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On New Year’s Day, let each person $p_i$ mingle until they find a group of
individuals $R_i$ where each individual in $R_i$ knows every other
individual in $R_i$, and $R_i$ is the largest of all such groups. By nature
of the friendships, this is guaranteed to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Count the size of each group $R_j$ formed. All cliques of size $n$ in $P$
for any $n \in \mathbb{N}$ are now known. Mapping the cliques in the graph
$G$ is trivial.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have we proved $P = NP$? Definitely not. Is a New Year universal aid policy a
great idea? Absolutely. Anyway, I wish you a fulfilling New Year!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>hafiz</name><email>ayaz.hafiz.1@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Most algorithms are designed for computation in a Turing machine. But Turing machines don’t encompass the physics of the universe, and of course there are algorithms designed to operate with other mechanics. Let’s call these other algorithms Analog Algorithms. Here’s one that claims to sort a set of numbers in linear timeIf executed on a simulating Turing machine..</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">seeing the big picture</title><link href="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/19/seeing-the-big-picture" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="seeing the big picture" /><published>2019-12-16T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-12-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/19/seeing-the-big-picture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/19/seeing-the-big-picture">&lt;p&gt;I’m not a good chess player. Perhaps causally, I was never very interested in it
either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But recently, I saw something new – chess is macro game. It’s a game between
sides, not between pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know why it took me 16 years to see this. Okay, it was definitely
some combination of taking the game for granted and a lack of further interest.
Those aren’t bad things – I think you should spend the most time on the things
you care most about. But they have led to at least two very scary results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When learning something new, it’s easy to step back and realize where
knowledge and integration gaps exist. I’ve known about chess my whole life,
and never stopped to back up.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This new perspective has reinvigorated my interest in chess and made me a
much stronger player.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many analogies you can derive here. So I challenge you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where else is the Big Picture being missed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth resp-iframe-container&quot; style=&quot;margin-top:2em&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe class=&quot;resp-iframe&quot; src=&quot;https://lichess.org/tv/frame&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>hafiz</name><email>ayaz.hafiz.1@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">I’m not a good chess player. Perhaps causally, I was never very interested in it either.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">spacing of square roots</title><link href="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/19/square-root-spacing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="spacing of square roots" /><published>2019-11-25T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-11-25T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/19/square-root-spacing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/19/square-root-spacing">&lt;p&gt;The distance between consecutive perfect squares is not uniform:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/squares/squares.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;First few perfect squares&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of the space between $n^2$ and $(n+1)^2$ is $2n + 1$, intuitively
evidenced by the growth in the spacing of the visualization above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, take a look at the distance between consecutive integer square roots:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/squares/sqroots.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;First few integer square roots&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, observe the spacing of integer square roots between $4$ and $9$ -
at one degree of precision, they are uniformly distributed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/squares/sqroot-4-to-9.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, this trend is significantly less intuitive. It makes sense in the “what
else is expected?” kind-of way, but that expectation isn’t very satisfying. So
here are a few other ways of understanding the spacing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1--from-the-spacing-of-squares&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#1--from-the-spacing-of-squares&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;el&quot;&gt;1:&lt;/span&gt;  From the Spacing of Squares&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For $n \in \mathbb{N}$, between $n^2$ and $(n+1)^2$ are the natural numbers
$n^2+1, n^2+2, \ldots, n^2 + 2n$. So between $n$ and $n+1$, there is a set of
integer square root reals
$S = \left\{\sqrt{n^2+1}, \sqrt{n^2+2}, \ldots, \sqrt{n^2 + 2n}\right\}$, and
$|S| = 2n$. Now, because $S_{i+1} &amp;gt; S_i$, we can make an
argument&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;pigeonhole&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;pigeonhole&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;somewhat similar
to the pigeonhole principle&lt;/span&gt; that for $n$ large, there are a large number of integer
square roots in the 1-unit interval $(n, n+1)$, giving the perception of uniformity
of the monotonically increasing set $S$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this explanation is not rigorous, and leaves one hungry for a more elegant
explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2--from-tangents&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#2--from-tangents&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;el&quot;&gt;2:&lt;/span&gt;  From Tangents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look at $f(x) = \sqrt{x}$:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/squares/sqroot-plot.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;$f(x) = \sqrt{x}$ and its tangents, $\frac{d}{dx} f(x)$ on $x\pm 0.5, x\in[0,16]$&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observe that for $n$ large, the slopes of the tangents of $f(x)$ at $n$ and
$n+1$ are small and very similar, implying&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that there is little variation in the value of the function at $n$ and $n+1$,
and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the variation between $n$ and $n+1$ is very similar to the variation between
$n+1$ and $n+2$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s enough needed for a beautiful reasoning of the relative uniformity of
integer square roots!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great thing about this kind of reasoning is it also explains the increasing
spacing between nodes of an exponential function, like $x^2$ or $e^x$. In both
of these cases, the slopes of pointwise tangent lines are increasing,
corresponding to the increasing rate of change in the spacing between e.g.
perfect squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h4 id=&quot;3--a-remix&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#3--a-remix&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;el&quot;&gt;3:&lt;/span&gt;  A remix&lt;/h4&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;To understand the previous reasoning a different way, consider
$f(x) = \sqrt{x + 1} - \sqrt{x}$.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/squares/sqroot-diff-plot.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;$f(x) = \sqrt{x + 1} - \sqrt{x}$&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The difference between consecutive integer square roots decreases
asymptotically, and thus we have that there is a relative uniformity in their
spacing – especially at large integer values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-application&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#an-application&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;An Application&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend asked what practical purpose knowing the spacing of integer square
roots serves. One useful application is in square root approximation - knowing
that integer square roots are approximately uniform especially at large numbers,
we can say that for an integer $q$, $\sqrt{q} \approx n + \frac{q-n^2}{2n+1}$,
where
$n = {\lfloor{\sqrt{q}}\rfloor}$&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;sqrt-example&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sqrt-example&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;For example, $10.724 = \sqrt{115} \approx 10.714 = \sqrt{100} + \frac{15}{21}$.&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>hafiz</name><email>ayaz.hafiz.1@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">The distance between consecutive perfect squares is not uniform:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">approximation with interpolating polynomials</title><link href="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/19/barycentric-interpolation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="approximation with interpolating polynomials" /><published>2019-11-15T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-11-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/19/barycentric-interpolation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ayazhafiz.com/articles/19/barycentric-interpolation">&lt;h2 id=&quot;lagrange-form&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#lagrange-form&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;Lagrange Form&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say you want to find an function approximating a set of data points&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;points&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;points&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;$(x_0, f_0), (x_1, f_1), \ldots, (x_n, f_n)$&lt;/span&gt;. One way to do this is to find a
polynomial $p_n \in \mathbb{P}_n$ satisfying the interpolation property&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;
p_n(x_i) = f_i\qquad i \in [0, n]
&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playing around a bit, we find that this polynomial can be written as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;
\begin{align*}
p_n(x) = &amp;\frac{(x - x_1) * (x - x_2) * \ldots * (x - x_n)}{(x_0 - x_1) * (x_0 - x_2) * \ldots * (x_0 - x_n)} f_0 \\
       &amp;+ \frac{(x - x_0) * (x - x_2) * \ldots * (x - x_n)}{(x_1 - x_0) * (x_1 - x_2) * \ldots * (x_1 - x_n)} f_1 \\
       &amp;+ \ldots \\
       &amp;+ \frac{(x - x_0) * (x - x_1) * \ldots * (x - x_{n-1})}{(x_n - x_0) * (x_n - x_1) * \ldots * (x_n - x_{n-1})} f_n \\
       = &amp;\sum_{i=0}^n \prod_{j=0\\j\ne i}^n \frac{x-x_j}{x_i-x_j} f_i\qquad j \in [0, n]
\end{align*}
&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is known as the Lagrange form of an interpolating polynomial, and is more commonly expressed as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;
\begin{align*}
p_n(x)    &amp;= \sum_{i=0}^n \ell_i(x)f_i \\
\ell_i(x) &amp;= \prod_{j=0\\j\ne i}^n \frac{x-x_j}{x_i-x_j}\qquad j \in [0, n]
\end{align*}
&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;custom-block&quot;&gt;
where $\ell_i$ is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lagrange_polynomial&quot;&gt;Lagrange
polynomial&lt;/a&gt; of degree $n$.&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;interpolationproof&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;&amp;#8853;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;interpolationproof&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt; To see that $p_n$ interpolates correctly, observe that

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;
\ell_i(x) = \begin{cases}
         1 &amp; x = x_i\\
         0 &amp; x \in \left\{x_0,\ldots,x_n\right\}\setminus \left\{x_i\right\}
         \end{cases}
&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

and so $p_n(x_i) = f_i + \sum_{j=0\\j\ne i}^n 0 f_j = f_i$.&lt;br /&gt;

It's not difficult to prove that $p_n$ is unique and of at most degree $n$, but we won't do that
here.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cost&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#cost&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;Cost&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lagrange form is not suitable for computation. Its construction requires massive
multiplication and division, which can be catastrophic for floating point precision.
The form is also not memoizable; evaluating $p_n(a)$ does not help in any part of the evaluation of
$p_n(b)$ when $b \ne a$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some more play, we can get a computationally-suitable equation known as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lagrange_polynomial#Barycentric_form&quot;&gt;Barycentric form&lt;/a&gt;
of an interpolating polynomial, defined as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;
p_n(x) = \frac{\sum_{i=0}^n \frac{\omega_i}{x-x_i} * f_i}{\sum_{i=0}^n \frac{\omega_i}{x-x_i}}
&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $w_i$ is a barycentric weight&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;
\omega_i(x) = \frac{1}{\prod_{j=0\\j\ne i}^n (x_i - x_j)}
&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because $\omega_i$ relies only on the explicitly-defined nodes $x_0, \ldots, x_n$, it does not need
to be recomputed for subsequent evaluations of $p_n$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;attempt-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#attempt-1&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;Attempt 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approximating $f(x) = \sin(4x\cos(8x))$ with various degrees of the Barycentric interpolant, using
equidistant interpolating nodes, gives&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/barycentric_interpolation/equidistant.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These polynomials definitely interpolate points of $f(x)$, but have the unfortunate tendency to blow up
around the interval endpoints. Note that the magnitude of the error at the edges grows with the degree of
the approximation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;runge&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#runge&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;Runge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This behavior is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Runge%27s_phenomenon&quot;&gt;Runge’s phenomenon&lt;/a&gt;, and
means that increasing the order of an approximating polynomial interpolant may not
improve its accuracy&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;wiki&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;wiki&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Why this occurs is beyond the scope of this post; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Runge%27s_phenomenon#Reason&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; gives a good explanation.&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to minimize Runge’s phenomenon is to densify the interpolating points near the endpoints of
the approximation interval&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;interval-endpoint&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;interval-endpoint&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Thereby more accurately fitting the
parts of the approximation affected by Runge’s phenomenon.&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chebyshev_nodes&quot;&gt;Chebyshev nodes&lt;/a&gt;
exhibit exactly this kind of edge-heavy density, making them very useful for polynomial interpolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a Barycentric interpolant with Chebyshev nodes yields a nice improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/barycentric_interpolation/chebyshev.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;convergence&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#convergence&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;Convergence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plotting the pointwise error of the Barycentric interpolant&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;cheb-nodes&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;cheb-nodes&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;generated with Chebyshev nodes&lt;/span&gt; approximating $f(x) = \sin(4x\cos(8x))$
suggests the polynomial interpolation is convergent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/barycentric_interpolation/error.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspection of the error
$l^2$ norms&lt;span class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;norm&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;norm&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Note that many other norms can be used for convergence analysis as well.&lt;/span&gt; suggests more:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Order   L2 norm
16      8.562880126489002
32      0.4243100460236342
64      5.324902188796007e-05
128     8.698460604825334e-14
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, the rate of convergence is pretty fast.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>hafiz</name><email>ayaz.hafiz.1@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">#Lagrange Form</summary></entry></feed>